Louisiana Miscellany
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Louisiana Miscellany 1724-1837
MSS30585
11 containers plus 5 oversize
5 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, reports, legal papers, maps, sketches, financial matter, a surveyor’s notebook, and other material relating to the early history of Louisiana under French, Spanish, and American control, including personal and official documents.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bénard de La Harpe, Jean Baptiste, 1683-1765. Journal historique de l'établissement des François á Louisiane. 1724.; Trudeau, Charles Laveau, approximately 1750-1816--Correspondence.
Subjects
Louisiana Purchase.
Places
France--Colonies--America.; Louisiana--Genealogy.; Louisiana--History--1803-1865.; Louisiana--History--To 1803.; Louisiana--History.; Louisiana--Surveys.; Spain--Colonies--America.; United States--History--19th century.
Provenance
The collection of Louisiana Miscellany was obtained by the Library of Congress from various sources in the 19th and 20th centuries.
Additional Guides
Notes relating to Jean Baptiste Bénard de la Harpe’s Journal historique de l ́établissement des François á Louisiane, in Container 1 of the collection, are available as a PDF.
Access and Restrictions
The Louisiana Miscellany is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on five reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Louisiana Miscellany, spanning the years 1724-1837, consists of correspondence, reports, legal papers, maps, sketches, financial matter, a surveyor’s notebook, and other material relating to the early history of Louisiana under French, Spanish, and American control. Among the personal as well as official documents are letters of Charles Laveau Trudeau, vital statistics from family Bibles and tombstones, papers relating to the purchase of Louisiana by the United States, and a manuscript copy of the French explorer Jean-Baptiste Bénard de la Harpe’s Journal historique de l ́etablissement des François á Louisiane.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by type of material or topic.
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 17,495
- Journal historique de l ́etablissement des François á Louisiane, by Jean-Baptiste Bénard de la Harpe, 1724 (Box OV 1, Reel 1)
- French and Spanish management of Louisiana (Box OV 2, Reel 1)
  - 1731-1734 (Box OV 2, Reel 1)
  - 1735-1753 (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - 1754-1762 See also oversize (Box OV 4, Reel 2-3)
  - 1763-1789 (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - 1790-1799 (Box 6, Reel 4)
- French, Spanish, and American management of Louisiana, 1800-1837, undated (Box 7, Reel 4-5)
- Value of Louisiana, 1763 (Box 8, Reel 5)
- Florida y Louisiana, 1780 [transcripts of 28 documents, 1493-1780] (Box 9, Reel 5)
- Louisiana, letters of Charles Trudeau, 1777-1816 (Box 10, Reel 5)
- Surveyor’s notebook, 1795-1797 (Box 11, Reel 5)
- Louisiana records (Box 12, Reel 5)
  - Vol. 1, vital statistics from family Bibles and other sources (Box 12, Reel 5)
  - Vol. 2, vital statistics from tombstones in cemeteries (Box 13, Reel 5)
  - Index to vols. 1-2 (Box 14, Reel 5)
- Papers in relation to the purchase of Louisiana, 1803-1804 (Box OV 15, Reel 5)
- Map (Container 4) Filmed in original sequence before removal to Oversize (Box OV 16, Reel 5)